HOW TO
BOIL AN EGG

You will need a small saucepan, an egg, a large spoon and a timer.

Fill the pan with sufficient water to cover the egg. Place the pan on the stove and bring the water to a rolling boil. Gently lower the egg into the water with the spoon and reduce the heat to a gentle boil. Cooking times are based on medium-sized eggs (for large eggs add 30 seconds extra):

• 6–7 minutes for soft-boiled.

• 9–10 minutes for a firmer set.

• 12–14 minutes for hard-boiled.

When done, lift the egg out of the water. For softer-boiled eggs, tap the top to crack the shell and prevent further cooking and serve. For hard-boiled eggs, drain the water from the pan and run the egg under cold water to cool it and prevent grey yolks.

HOW TO SEPARATE EGGS

Have two bowls, a saucer and a small cup ready. Carefully crack an egg onto the saucer. Place the cup over the yolk to contain it, then drain the egg white into one bowl. Tip the yolk into the remaining bowl. Repeat this process until all the eggs required are separated. Don’t skip the cup and saucer process—one broken yolk in the whites will ruin the whole batch.

HOW TO
MAKE A SALAD DRESSING

You will need good quality olive oil, white wine vinegar or lemon juice, salt, Dijon mustard, runny honey and a clean, empty jam jar with a lid. This dressing will go well with any kind of leaf or raw vegetable salad; your friends will beg you for the recipe.

As a base, use three parts olive oil to one part white wine vinegar or lemon juice and put these into the jar. The oil coats the salad ingredients and the acid in the vinegar or lemon cuts through the oiliness and adds zing.

Add a pinch of salt, half a teaspoon of Dijon mustard and half a teaspoon of runny honey. If you don’t have honey, dissolve half a teaspoon of sugar in a tiny amount of boiling water.

Put the lid on the jar and shake the ingredients to blend them. Taste and adjust, if necessary, by adding more of any of the above ingredients as required. This quantity will be sufficient for one serving bowl of salad.

You can vary the ingredients as you wish. Use red wine, balsamic or cider vinegar instead of white wine vinegar or lemon. Add a pinch of dried oregano or a grind of black pepper. Try grainy French mustard instead of Dijon.

Remember to give the dressing a good shake before you pour it over the salad as the ingredients will separate, or serve in a jug and give your guests a spoon for stirring. Any leftover dressing can be stored for up to three months in the fridge.

HOW TO
COOK A STEAK

Remove the steak from the fridge an hour before cooking so it comes up to room temperature. Rub the meat all over with olive oil and season with salt and pepper. Heat a thick-based frying pan or griddle. Make sure it is extremely hot before adding the steak (if you can hold your hand 6 inches from the pan/griddle for more than a second it’s not hot enough). Once the steak has been added to the pan, turn the meat once a minute for even cooking until done as desired.

TOP TIPS

• The most popular cuts of steak are rump and rib-eye for depth of flavor, while pricier sirloin and fillet are chosen for tenderness.

• Fillet steak is cut thick so it may require a minute or so more cooking time. A steak served medium-rare to medium will be juicy and full of flavor. Cook for 6 minutes for medium-rare or 4 minutes for a thin steak. You can always cook steak a little longer if it’s too pink but you can’t undo it if it is overcooked.

• Well-done steak can risk being tough and dry; however, if you prefer not to see any pinkness to your meat then a longer cooking time will suit you. Allow 8 minutes in total, depending on thickness.

• Test the steak with your finger. A medium-rare steak will have a bit of give, while a well-done steak will feel firm to the touch. Once the steak is cooked, rest it on a plate for 2–4 minutes to allow the juices to flow. This settling process encourages a tender finish. Add a little extra oil or butter if preferred.

HOW TO
STUFF AND ROAST A CHICKEN

Hygiene is extremely important when handling raw chicken as it carries bacteria that are only killed off when the bird is thoroughly cooked. Throw away packaging carefully and wash any utensils or surfaces that have been in contact with the chicken with hot, soapy water—not forgetting your hands.

1 Heat the oven to 375ºF.

2 Lift the neck flap of the chicken, at the end nearest the wings, and fill the stretchy skin with as much stuffing as will fit into it. Tuck the flap end under.

3 Place the chicken in a baking tray. Rub softened butter all over the breast and legs and season with salt, pepper and a sprinkling of herbs. Roasting time depends on weight. A 3-pound chicken will take around 1 hour and 20 minutes.

4 Check it’s done by inserting a sharp knife where the inner thigh and breast meet. The juices should run clear with no trace of pink. Lift the chicken onto a serving dish or board and let it rest for 10–15 minutes before carving.

TRADITIONAL SAGE AND ONION STUFFING

1 Peel and finely chop a small onion.

2 Add in approximately 3.5 ounces of breadcrumbs, 1 teaspoon of sage (fresh or dried), salt and pepper.

3 Add enough water to bind the mixture together: around 2–3 tablespoons.

HOW TO
REMOVE STAINS

• Act fast to avoid permanent staining and use the right product for the type of stain. Wash after treatment.

• Soak blood stains in cold water immediately.

• Solvents are needed to treat substances that are not water soluble, such as paint, tar or make-up. Solvent products that specially treat stains are readily available. To treat a stain with solvents, place one pad of white kitchen towel, or a clean cloth, under the stain and use another one to dab at it with the solvent.

• Pen marks will lift off when dabbed with hair spray.

• Rust can be removed with white vinegar or lemon juice.

• Apply white vinegar diluted with water to grass stains.

• Soak acid food stains like tomato for 30 minutes in white vinegar. Rinse and put a little detergent directly onto the stain before washing.

• Talcum powder absorbs grease and oil marks on clothes or suede shoes. Pile on and leave for 20 minutes. Shake off the powder and bang out any residue by hand. Repeat for stubborn stains.

• If you’re out and about, blot the worst off a food stain. Unless it’s a dry-clean only item, dab with water to dilute—this makes it easier to wash out later. Don’t rub at the stain as this will push it further into the fibers.

• Heavy-duty white cottons can be bleached to remove stains but delicate fabrics can’t withstand this treatment.

• Stain removers can take out dye on colored fabric. Test on an inside seam before applying.

HOW TO
CLEAN A WINDOW

Grimy windows are harder to clean, so to keep things easy clean all the glass twice a year and bring extra light into your home.

Clean windows on a dull day as strong sunlight can dry windows too quickly, leaving streaks.

Before starting, clear the space around the window you intend to clean. Protect the floor or surrounding furniture from water splashes. Remove dust and cobwebs with a brush.

Squirt a little dish soap into a bucket of warm water—too many soap suds are harder to wash off the window. Alternatively, add two tablespoons of vinegar to the water. Wet a sponge and squeeze well before you apply it to the glass to avoid drips. Rub the sponge over each pane, inside and out, to remove the dirt.

Purpose-made window cleaners can be sprayed directly onto glass and polished off, but strong versions can damage paintwork or soft furnishings.

Work a rubber-bladed squeegee down the glass from top to bottom in an S-shaped motion to push the water down and off the surface. Clean the blade from time to time with a rag to remove the dirt.

Use a clean, slightly damp microfiber cloth, chamois leather, or a worn-out T-shirt to take off any remaining water. An old trick of professional window cleaners is to use scrunched up newspaper to add sparkle and shine to dried windows, although you will end up with newsprint on your hands!

HOW TO
REMOVE CHEWING GUM FROM FURNITURE

There’s a variety of ways to shift hardened chewing gum off furniture. Here are a couple that are simple to do and least likely to cause damage.

WOODEN FURNITURE

• Oil method: Soak a piece of paper towel or a clean cloth with vegetable oil and push it against all sides of the blob of gum. The oil should work its way under the edges and release the gum’s grip. Polish off any residual oil once the gum has been removed.

• Ice method: Put some ice cubes into a small plastic food or freezer bag. Hold the bag against the gum to freeze it solid. Then lever the gum off the furniture with a blunt knife, being careful not to dig into the wood.

UPHOLSTERY FABRIC

• Sticky tape method: Strong duct tape is the best type to use for this job. Cut a piece and apply the sticky side to the gum to pull it away from the fabric. Keep repeating with clean pieces of tape until all the gum is gone.

• Ice method: Using ice to freeze the gum should also work on furnishing fabric. After the ice has worked its magic—and if the fabric is washable—finish with a little warm, soapy water then rinse and pat dry. If the gum’s stuck to a cushion cover, take the cover off the pad before treating.

HOW TO
GET STAINS OUT OF A CARPET OR UPHOLSTERY

UPHOLSTERY

If fabric is removable and washable, sponge the stain with cold water or soak the fabric in a bowl of cold water for approximately 30 minutes. Treat with pre-wash stain remover before machine washing according to the fabric type.

For fixed furnishing fabric, blot the stain as much as possible. Mix a small squirt of dish soap with cool water so it’s not too soapy and sponge the stain with a clean, white cloth. Blot up all the liquid and repeat the cleaning process until the stain has disappeared. Sponge with cold water to remove any soap and blot dry.

CARPETS

Act particularly fast on red wine stains! Blot the stain continuously with dry, white paper towel until you can’t see any color on the paper. Remove a shoe and press lightly with your foot on the paper towel to help blot. Don’t rub, as this will set the stain further into the carpet fibers. Add a little water and continue to blot. This technique can be employed for any type of liquid carpet stains.

For food stains, gently lift off thick spills and chunky pieces with a blunt knife before attempting to blot. Use diluted dish soap (as directed in the “Upholstery” section above) or spray with a good carpet stain remover, following the manufacturer’s directions. Repeat if necessary. Vacuum when the area has dried.

HOW TO
CLEAN AN OVEN

This isn’t a job that most of us relish, but it needn’t be hard if performed at regular intervals and the sparkling result can be satisfying.

First, check whether your oven has an auto-clean function (you may save yourself some work). However, even if it does, you’ll still need to clean the oven racks. Remove these, including any vertical hanging racks, and soak them in hot, soapy water in the sink.

For manual cleaning, start by wiping away any loose debris. Then either spray on the chemical cleaner or try a more eco-friendly version (suitable only for lightly soiled ovens); leave it to work for the prescribed time with the door shut. Always check which cleaners are recommended for your oven make and avoid putting any cleaner on the element.

Alternatively, try the steam-cleaning method. You will need the bottom rack in place for this. Fill a large baking tray or oven-proof dish with water and place on the rack. Turn the oven on at its highest temperature setting. After 30 minutes turn the oven off and leave it to cool with the door shut. Then take a damp cloth and wipe down the inside, not forgetting the inside of the door. The steam will have done a good job of loosening grease and grime so this should be easy.

HOW TO
PREPARE A WALL FOR PAINTING

Painting a room is relatively quick to do and the finish can look professional if the preparation is done well.

Move all the furniture to the center of the room and cover with old sheets, disposable dust covers or newspaper to guard against paint splatters. Cover the floor well with similar protection, taping protective coverings to the floor edges before painting skirting boards to protect the floor from paint drips.

Dust walls and all paintwork—including chair rails, picture railings, moldings and baseboards—to prevent particles from clogging up the new paint. Wipe down kitchen and bathroom walls with a sponge and soapy water to remove grime and grease and leave to dry before painting. Fill cracks or holes with filler (see “Fill a crack or hole” above) and scrape away any cracked or flaky paint.

Protect window frames, baseboards, picture rails, light switches, wall light fittings and power outlets with closely fitting strips of masking tape. Take time to apply the tape carefully as this will allow you to paint the walls speedily.

HOW TO
CHANGE A LIGHT BULB

Switch off the lamp or light fitting and be sure the bulb is cool before removing it.

Unscrew the bulb from the socket—or if it has a bayonet fitting, hold the bulb and push it in and turn counter-clockwise until it releases. Do this with a firm grip on the bulb and a gentle action to avoid shattering the glass.

Replace with a new bulb, making sure it has the recommended wattage for the fitting to prevent overheating or scorching fabric shades. Screw firmly into place—or for the bayonet type, line up the twin prongs of the bulb over the two slots in the fitting, push them in and twist the bulb clockwise into place. Turn on the light switch to check that it is working.

Exceptionally long-lasting, eco-friendly bulbs (LEDs) are rapidly replacing compact fluorescent light bulbs (CFLs)—the early green solution to traditional incandescent light bulbs. These newer LEDs can last up to 35 times longer.

To change a downlight bulb, flick the light switch to the off position. Get a sturdy ladder, and some newspaper to protect carpet from a possible soot shower. Most fittings are spring-loaded and just need grasping round the outer rim with your fingers and pulling down gently, while supporting the light bulb. Ease the old bulb out of its socket and fit the new one in. Nestle it into the fitting and push it back into the ceiling.

For light fittings situated in tall ceilings or high landings you may need an electrician’s help.

HOW TO
DRY OUT A WET MOBILE PHONE/LAPTOP

The trick with all electronic devices is to let them dry out without pressing any buttons. Pressing them risks letting more water seep into the device, possibly causing irreparable damage, so employ restraint: it might save your gadget. It’s equally important to remove the battery to prevent damage from short-circuiting, so on a device with a built-in battery you will have to press buttons to shut it down.

For phones, remove the cover, if there is one, and the SIM card. Dry the device with a towel or paper towel. Fill an airtight container with uncooked instant rice or couscous and bury your phone in the middle. Pop the lid on and leave the grains to draw out the moisture for 24–48 hours. It’s important to be patient because if water remains now it may cause rust and corrosion later.

Laptops are more at risk from drink spillages, so it’s sensible to keep drinks well out of range. A laptop might survive an encounter with a glass of water but the sugar content of fizzy drinks and wine could be your electronic lifeline’s sticky end. Disconnect it from the power source and any cables. Once you’ve shut it down and removed any batteries, leave it open and turn it upside down; tilt to drain out the liquid. Keep it upside down while blow-drying it with a hairdryer on the “cool” setting for 15–20 minutes. Leave it in a good position to dry for 24 hours (maybe inside an airing cupboard) before attempting to turn it on.

HOW TO
CHANGE WINDSHIELD WIPERS

Change your wipers at least once a year. It is easier to replace the complete blades, rather than just the rubber inserts. Most cars have the U hook type of blades but check your vehicle’s manual for instructions before you attempt to remove them.

Take the old blades into the shop with you when you go to buy the new ones and check whether they’re compatible with your car’s make and model before you purchase. You may be surprised to find the driver’s side wiper is longer than that of the passenger’s side; this is normal.

Change the blades with the wipers stopped in a vertical position on the windshield. Half-turn your ignition on to position the blades.

Carefully lift a blade away from the windshield until it clicks into a right-angled position, then turn the blade until it is at a right-angle to the wiper arm. Depress the small clip that joins the blade to the wiper arm while moving the blade downwards and then upwards to unhook it. Gently lower the arm against the windshield. Repeat with the other blade.

To fit the new blades, hold each one at right-angles to its wiper arm, feed it through the gap in the arm and push it upwards into the U hook until it clips into place.

Replace the wiper blades outside the shop you bought them from in case you need assistance. Don’t throw away your old wipers until you are sure the new ones work.

HOW TO
CHECK YOUR CAR’S TIRE PRESSURE

Keeping tires properly inflated is key to braking performance, grip and reduced fuel consumption. Check them once a month when you fill up with fuel.

How much air to add depends on your specific car make and model and the load you are carrying. A car heavily-laden with vacation luggage and four passengers will need more pressure than normal. Follow the manufacturer’s recommendation in your car’s manual.

Park next to the tire pressure gauge at a gas station. You may have to pay a small charge for this service. Find the tire valve sticking out of the wheel rim. Unscrew the cap.

Pressure is measured in pounds per square inch (PSI) and bar. The machine should display in both and may have a control button so you can switch to your preferred type of measurement. The plus and minus signs on the machine allow you to set the pressure you want.

Go around the car, attaching the tire pressure gauge’s hose to each tire in turn. The machine will check the pressure that you set and pump in more air, as needed. It will beep and stop when the pre-set level has been reached. When all tires have been checked return the hose to the machine and replace the valve caps.

HOW TO
PARALLEL PARK

When you learned to drive, your instructor would have taught you how to parallel park. However, if you haven’t had to do it much, here’s a refresher.

1 Choose a space that is two car lengths long to reverse into—when you’ve honed your parking technique you’ll be confident about tackling smaller spaces.

2 Drive up alongside the parked car in front of the space you’re pulling into. Stop when the back of your vehicle roughly lines up with that of the parked car. Check your mirrors to make sure that it’s safe to move, then indicate.

3 Put your car into reverse gear and move back, turning the steering wheel to the right if you’re parking on the right-hand side of the road and to the left if you’re parking on the left-hand side. This will point the rear end of your vehicle towards the curb at an angle. Don’t turn too sharply into the curb because you’ll only have to pull out and start again (plus you risk scraping the parked car).

4 Keep maneuvering back slowly. Aim the back corner of the car at the curb two-thirds of your car’s length back into the space, before you turn the wheel the other way.

5 Now you are in the space, you can move the car forward or back to make sure that you don’t hog a big space or box in either of the parked cars to the front of or behind you.

HOW TO
HAGGLE IN SHOPS OR MARKETS

Most shops have set prices and if you are dealing with general sales staff they probably won’t have the authority to offer discounts, unless you are buying in high volume or spending a great deal of money. However, there are exceptions: for example, on large price-tag items like cars, fitted kitchens, furniture and major appliances, where there is an expectation of discounts or extras.

It’s always worth asking for a deal. Say to a sales assistant that you’re interested in buying a particular bed and ask if a mattress protector or a couple of pillows can be thrown in, too.

Owner-managers of independent shops may be more willing to offer discounts to regular shoppers, or if you are seen to be indecisive about buying three or more high-price items. Towards the end of a sales period you may be able to secure an extra percentage discount on an item if the shop is keen to clear stock.

Markets are better hunting grounds for hagglers looking to lower the asking price. In many countries haggling at market stalls is expected. Remember: only haggle if you are serious about buying. Think about what price you are prepared to pay; between counter offers this should end up around midway between the seller’s proposed price and your lowest starting offer. Be prepared to walk away if you can’t agree a price.

Do be realistic about when you can push for money off purchases in stores and remember that it pays to be polite when asking.

HOW TO
MANAGE YOUR FINANCES

To manage and plan your spending, first work out a budget. Record your income and what you spend each month. For example:

• Recurring monthly payments: Rent/mortgage, utilities, taxes, pension, loans.

• Daily and general expenses: Travel, food, fuel.

• Extras: Entertainment and leisure, vacations, Christmas, parties, unforeseen bills.

• Savings: Money for future plans and contingency for some of the extras.

Being aware of what you’re spending makes it easier to work out what to trim. For example, cutting back on take-out and coffee shop treats could fund a fantastic vacation.

Insure against the worst happening: it can save you from possible mega bills if it does.

Try to only have one credit card and put on it only what you can afford to pay off each month in full. The credit facility can be a lifeline in emergencies, but not if your card is maxed out.

Download any of the well-rated apps available to manage your own spending, or to divvy up expenditure with others.

Start saving for your pension as soon as possible—doing this as a regular drip-feed of savings from your twenties onwards will have a dramatically better outcome than starting in your thirties. Financial wizards estimate that you need to put aside 12.5 percent of your salary for 40 years before you retire to build up a safe pension pot. Part-time work in later life is a developing trend, but this depends on continued good health and the ability to secure that employment.

HOW TO
PAY OFF DEBT

Borrowings for mortgages, student loans or loans for specific items are positive, since they reward you with the gain of a home, a degree, or a useful or desired purchase—as long as you can afford the payments. However, you’re in the danger zone if you’re running up an overdraft without having enough income to clear it. Unless it’s tackled, debt can set you back for years due to high interest charges; it may also give you lower credit scores.

A firm action plan is required:

• Calculate what you owe to whom. Don’t leave anything out.

• Draw up a budget including a schedule for repaying your debts. Prioritize: items such as mortgages, utilities and taxes come first.

• Pay off as much as you can. If you only make the minimum monthly payments it will take you considerably longer to make any headway with the overall sum.

• Don’t borrow any more money or incur any additional debts until you’ve repaid your existing ones.

• Curb your spending by cutting up your credit and store cards, or giving them to someone you trust for safekeeping. Take a set sum of cash out of your bank account once a week and live off that only.

• Switch to a cheaper credit card or loan provider to keep the interest from racking up on your current debt. Some offer 0 percent interest for an initial period. Note when the 0 percent period is up and switch again. Check for balance transfer fees and annual charges.

HOW TO
WRITE A THANK-YOU NOTE

A thank-you note needn’t be long, but a promptly sent handwritten one goes down well—particularly with the older generation. With your contemporaries, you may get away with a text message or an email, but a handwritten note shows more consideration.

A friend might ask you to celebrate a milestone birthday, join them on vacation or invite you to their wedding, but if it’s their parents who are paying it’s to them that thanks are due.

If you don’t possess headed paper or cards, a note card will do fine. Choose your best pen—black or blue ink is preferable—write your address in the top right-hand corner, put the date underneath and add the salutation on the left-hand side.

If witty words don’t come naturally to you, plan what you are going to write beforehand. Start by thanking the recipient—for the invite or the present in question—and then reference memorable highlights. For example: the host’s generosity; how much you enjoyed yourself/liked your present; the quality of the food/wine/entertainment/setting/speeches; and who you enjoyed meeting. Don’t stint on complimentary adjectives; they may feel a little over the top when putting pen to paper but it will give the recipient a glow of pleasure to read them. Expand with your hope to see them soon, a return invitation or good wishes for a forthcoming event in their lives.

Sign off with “Yours sincerely”, “Best wishes” or “Love”, as appropriate, before your name.

HOW TO
WHISTLE WITH YOUR FINGERS

It will take a bit of practice to produce more than a splutter so be prepared to experiment until you find your personal sweet spot to achieve an ear-splitting whistle. Don’t give up and you’ll get there in the end.

Choose the finger combination that feels the most natural to you. Most people plump for one of the following:

• Forming a closed “C” shape with the thumb and forefinger of one hand.

• Making an “A” frame shape with the index finger of each hand.

• Both the index and middle finger of each hand.

The technique is the same for any of these.

Start with clean hands. Cover your bottom set of teeth with your bottom lip. The harder you press your lip down into your teeth, the louder your whistle will be. With your chosen finger shape, push down on your lip with the first joint of your digits. Curl your tongue back and use your fingers to keep it there.

Take a deep breath to fill up your lungs with air and close your lips together. Exhale as fast as you can through the gap between your fingers.

Keep practicing until you achieve a good result. Take a break if you feel dizzy from too many in-and-out exhalations. Adjust the position of your fingers, lips, mouth and tongue until you find what works for you.

HOW TO
CONVERSE WITH A YOUNGER PERSON

Here’s a trick for starting interaction with little children to whom you’ve just been introduced. Resist making direct eye contact. Sit down on the floor a short distance away and start to be busy with an activity, within their line of sight. Play intently with one of the child’s toys, have a pretend conversation with a teddy or tussle a ball in the jaws of a friendly dog. Most children will start to be intrigued. Carry on and give the child an occasional smile. Before long, even the shyest child will want to join in. The opportunity to talk about what you’re doing, or their favorite thing, will soon follow.

Older children can be coaxed into conversation by focusing on what they like—best TV shows, favored apps, closest friends, sports followed, favorite foods and pets are all good bets.

Young teens can feel shy around older teenagers. You may recall feeling overshadowed by the seeming glamour and confidence of those further up the developmental chain. If you are now in this position, a genuine interest in them and their opinions can make them shine. Develop a rapport with them by drawing them out to talk about their passions.

Older teenagers tend to be easier to talk with and there is plenty to talk about: their plans for college, university, work experience and travel. Some may already be working or be on an apprentice scheme. Conversation gambits can therefore be naturally more varied.

HOW TO
SAY, “I’M SORRY”

Saying “sorry” is a challenging but inevitable part of life. Here are some tips to make saying that little word a bit easier.

Say sorry whenever it is warranted. It can often go a long way to mollifying an increasingly tense situation.

Confess when you’ve done the wrong thing. Don’t think that an apology demeans you in any way; in fact, not apologizing is much more likely to do so. Saying “I’m really sorry” doesn’t automatically lead to forgiveness when you have hurt someone or done something wrong; it’s a step in the right direction though.

Mean what you say. Do resist saying “I’m sorry” in a sarcastic tone, it tells the other person you think they are unnecessarily touchy and that they are wrong to expect any kind of apology. Instead, aim to be sincere.

If the situation that required the apology is more serious, you may need a strategy for moving forward in a positive way with the person or people concerned. Ask if there is anything you can do to make it up to the other person. Do you need to state that you will modify your behavior or promise not to let a similar situation occur in future? This is part of reassuring others that you are genuine in your intentions not to repeat the same mistake.

HOW TO
SAY, “THANK YOU”

“Thank you” is one of the most powerful phrases in your lexicon. Never neglect to say it frequently as an act of appreciation for what others have done for you, even on the smallest scale. Express your thanks on notepaper, or in the form of a tangible gift if appropriate, and you will build a reputation for being considerate and kind. Always be sincere when you offer thanks.

Show thanks and gratitude by text or email when work colleagues, clients and comparative strangers have helped you, or if you are asking for their time and assistance. Thank and praise your colleagues to their face, whatever level they are—not just for big pieces of project work or new business wins, but for everyday things like finding something for you, adapting an image or rewording something, or putting themselves out for you when they have a pile of other things to do. Go further when you can and tell them what a good job they have done. Watch them smile in appreciation.

It costs very little to say thank you but it makes a world of difference to others and to how others perceive you. (And don’t forget that other essential—to frequently say “please”!)

HOW TO
SAY, “NO”

Are you a pushover when someone asks you to do something? Can you cope when you are asked for a favor out of your comfort zone? For example, a friend wants a loan: your mind is screaming “no” but you don’t know how to sidestep the request. In this circumstance, it helps to refuse in a way that doesn’t leave the friend feeling they’re untrustworthy. For instance, an all-encompassing, “I’ve made it a rule never to lend money to friends.” Explanations phrased in a way that don’t sound like personal rejections are a good strategy. On some occasions, offering an alternative works well. When asked by your boss to do an additional task in the workplace that’s not going to fit your workload, say, for instance, “Project X is what I’m working on now, can this wait until afterwards, or do you want me to reprioritize?” They might not have remembered you have so much to do and you are not refusing to help. A friend might ask, “Can I bring my new girlfriend round to dinner, too?” If this doesn’t suit say, “I’ve already got as many as I can manage coming but why don’t we arrange a night out together, so I can meet her?” Being able to say “no” is one of the most valuable skills you can learn. It will make sure you don’t take on too much, keep you from feeling resentful and allow you to prioritize what’s important in your life.

HOW TO
ASK SOMEONE OUT

A first date is about reaching out to learn more about the other person if they are a stranger, or an affirmation that you are taking a deeper interest in someone you already know. Perhaps your motivation is based on the desire for a physical relationship.

Just because you ask someone out once, it doesn’t mean that you will spend a lifetime together. On the other hand, it might be just what you are looking for and this obviously can and does happen!

It’s acceptable to text someone to suggest meeting up. Face-to-face encounters will require you to do the talking. Suggesting a decisive plan makes a good start—for example, “Would you like to come with me to the Skyline Bar on Thursday night for drinks and then to Oka for dinner?” You’ll soon gauge from their reaction if you are being turned down, or whether offering an alternative night would be fine; it’s better to know where you stand and take a refusal on the chin—you can’t win them all. Alternatively, play safe and suggest coffee or lunch as this is a more ambiguous social setting, then fix a time and place.

Bear in mind that noisy venues and going to a movie on a first date are not the best places to choose if you want to talk.

HOW TO
BREAK UP WITH SOMEONE

Do as you would be done by. That means no cowardly text or email, or engineering a conversation to make them dump you. Do it face-to-face as direct contact will help the other person process why you are leaving with less room for ambiguity.

Be considerate about timing your break-up. Hang on if your other half is in exam mode, just lost their job or received other major bad news. Avoid pre-Christmas, Valentine’s Day or birthday break-ups if possible, too.

Call the meeting and clarify that you want to talk about your relationship. Ideally, avoid public spaces. Think about what you want to say before you meet and how the other person might react. Be as honest as possible but not deliberately hurtful. Get to the point and be clear that you are serious about ending things to avoid giving hope that you might change your mind. Prolonged break-ups can be messy for both of you.

If you’ve made your point and given the chance for questions to be asked, but your ex is saying the same thing repeatedly, be firm: state that you’ve said what you needed to say and now it’s time for you to go.

Whether you stay in touch, follow each other on social media, or still share friends is down to both of you. Sometimes it’s easier to get over a relationship if all contact is severed.

HOW TO
SHAKE HANDS

A handshake is a way to introduce yourself to another person and connect with them in a sincere and friendly way. Traditionally it’s a sign that you come in peace, stemming from the days when men carried swords and daggers—a handshake created a bond of trust as it was proof that you weren’t holding a weapon.

It’s customary to let the person in a higher position of authority take the lead on the handshake by extending their hand out first for you to clasp in yours, firmly without exerting unnecessary pressure. The actual shaking part of the greeting should only last for a few seconds. Look to the initiator to break contact before you do.

Look the other person in the eye as you shake hands and maintain that contact as your hands part. Don’t cup their elbow or touch them with your other hand in a business situation, or if you’re in doubt in a social situation.

Bone-crushing grips are unwelcome and can be unpleasantly painful for those on the receiving end, particularly so for women with slender hands and be-ringed fingers. On the other hand, limp handshakes brand the giver as weak and are not ideal either. Try not to show you mind if you are presented with a sweaty palm.

When doing business abroad, check up on handshake protocol—there can be wide variations.

For instance, never offer your left hand in the Middle East; in China shake hands with the oldest people first; don’t shake hands in Thailand!

HOW TO
CONTROL YOUR TEMPER

Anger is a normal emotion. Even the most equable of us can find our temperament strained to the point where we lash out. However, it can cause problems to you and others around you if you find it difficult to keep it under control. Equally, simmering and sulking is perturbing to others around you, particularly if they are nothing to do with the source of your anger.

Anger management is not about suppressing anger, but rather finding ways of recognizing when your temper is flaring up and channelling control. The idea is that instead of blowing your top in a way you may later regret, you implement a strategy to diffuse the anger and communicate your feelings effectively.

Next time you feel anger rising, try counting to ten before you react. Give yourself a moment to assess the situation. Is your temper justified? Could you have misunderstood something? Is there another perspective to consider? Walk away for a minute or two, do some deep breathing and come back. If you’re frustrated with repeat behavior from a family member, friend or colleague, present a solution.

Anger can be ingrained in your personality, but relaxation techniques and regular exercise can help reduce tension and stress levels and refresh your mind-set.

If you find yourself angry with life on a daily basis, there may be some underlying unhappiness that’s causing you distress which should be addressed. Finding a level of contentment can diminish angry thoughts and negativity.

HOW TO
MAKE A DECISION

Making the right decision can be full of responsibility. It can be the difference between success and failure, or favoring a morally decent course of action over personal gain. Others may be affected or the decision, once taken, could be irreversible.

Fear of the outcome can make people timid about making a decision—this can drag out the decision-making process, sometimes resulting in a lost opportunity. By all means mull over the possibilities, but don’t lose too much momentum.

Look objectively at a decision to be made by formulating a plan. List pros and cons in two separate columns for decisions that are straight choices between two options. Committing these to a list, rather than leaving them to swirl around in your head, can focus your thoughts and speed up the process.

Where there is a range of alternatives to consider, list these too and add some questions. For example:

• Who will it affect and how?

• What are the consequences now and in the future?

• What could go wrong?

Look further than the immediate solution that presents itself, as it won’t necessarily be the best. Gather all the information to help you decide. Take professional advice where appropriate. Discuss any dilemmas with neutral parties and factor in their reactions and advice. Even just voicing the options to others can lead you to think differently about the decision.

HOW TO
DEFEND YOURSELF IN AN ARGUMENT

We all get yelled at from time to time. When it happens to you, seemingly out of left field, it can be hard not to snap back automatically.

Try hard to listen to what is being said to you, without interruption. Bristling with anger yourself and reacting badly could escalate the problem. Look for logic. Does your verbal attacker have a point? Is there something that you have done, even unwittingly, that might have caused upset? In which case, a quick and sincere apology normally works better than an attempt to justify your actions.

You may be facing a serial fight-picker desiring your reaction, even to the point of wanting your negative attention. If you react defensively to their opening complaint, the attacker is unlikely to back down—they’ll continue with a long list of other related “sins” you have committed. Try responding in a way that doesn’t allow them to carry on picking a fight.

Here are a couple of examples with different strategies to try. “Why don’t you make more of an effort about your appearance?” Tell a long, rambling story so they lose interest, that begins something like this, “That could be because of an incident that happened a long time back. One day…” “Why can I never find my phone? What have you done with it?” Respond with a neutral statement such as, “It can be very annoying when you can’t find things.” You may need to keep going with similar variations before your attacker runs out of steam.